[SPEAKER_04]: So, this is an excerpt from Majjhima Nikaya 41.
[SPEAKER_04]: Householders, there are three kinds of bodily conduct not in accordance with the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_04]: Unrighteous conduct, there are four kinds of verbal conduct not in accordance with the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_04]: And there are three kinds of mental conduct not in accordance with the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's when somebody kills living beings, when somebody takes by way of theft the wealth and property of others, when he misconducts himself in sensual pleasures,
[SPEAKER_04]: Meaning, he has improper sexual relationships.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then, there are four kinds of verbal conduct, not in the course of the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_04]: When somebody lies, when they... when they speak maliciously, so as to divide groups, divide one group from the other group, or divide the other group from the first group.
[SPEAKER_04]: When one speaks harshly, and then when they speak basically useless talk, or frivolous talk.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, there are three kinds of mental conduct, not in accordance with the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_04]: The first one is covetousness.
[SPEAKER_04]: The second one is ill will.
[SPEAKER_04]: And the third one is wrong view.
[SPEAKER_04]: And here is the part of interest.
[SPEAKER_04]: It says,
[SPEAKER_04]: There is nothing given, nothing offered, nothing sacrificed, no fruit or result of good and bad actions, no this world, no other world, no mother, no father, no beings who were reborn spontaneously, no good and virtuous recluses and brahmins in the world who have themselves realized by direct knowledge and the claim of this world and the other world.
[SPEAKER_04]: Those are the three types of mental misconduct.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, householders, it is by reason of such conduct, not in accordance with the dhamma, that some beings here, on the dissolution of the body after death, reappear in states of deprivation, an unhappy destination, a perdition, even in hell.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, basically, the... it's something that people might overlook, that
[SPEAKER_00]: The wrong view is on the same level as these actions that a person might have overcome and, you know, just through basic virtue and keeping the five precepts, but...
[SPEAKER_00]: It sounds like a very coarse or crude kind of view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nobody actually believes that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It sounds as if it's something that everybody would have gone beyond just by becoming a Buddhist, for example.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that wrong view is actually something that is much more deeply rooted and much more
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, if you fully abandon that view, you would be a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there have... there has to be traces of that view in your experience, even if you don't outright tell others like, no, I believe that there is nothing given, or I believe that there is no mother and no father.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is some trace of that in you, if you are not a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, that...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I thought we could explore how would those views manifest, given that it's not the obvious intention to believe these things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, here we start with the beginning, like there's nothing given, nothing offered, nothing sacrificed.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I set a wrong view.
[SPEAKER_04]: And what does that mean exactly?
[SPEAKER_02]: Does it mean to say... Is it talking about... like...
[SPEAKER_00]: What it's really saying is it makes no difference whether you give something to someone or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's connected with the second point.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no result of good and bad actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, it just makes no difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just go through life and it's kind of like random.
[SPEAKER_00]: Things that happen to you are a result of just
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, random things happening, the world, chaos theory.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some cosmic force or other.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, it basically... the reason why that view is incompatible with the right view is because, I mean, the most basic point is it just takes away the fact that you are responsible for your own suffering, most important.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you can't accept, it's not just like the fact that you won't be making merit.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you have that wrong view, it's the fact that it blocks the understanding of the dhamma itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because then you... like, how are you going to recognize that you, yourself... Because results of good and bad action doesn't just mean bodily and verbal action.
[SPEAKER_00]: As this itself said, it talks about mental action as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how will you purify yourself?
[SPEAKER_00]: If you don't believe that the actions that you're doing have results, it's just the most basic thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that first one is always enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, what does it mean, for example, not to believe that there is a mother and father?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, most generally,
[SPEAKER_01]: Things in the world come with their own significance.
[SPEAKER_01]: And in terms of one's relationship with human beings, one's father and mother are... they have a special significance.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so it is important to
[SPEAKER_01]: Recognize, on the most general level, things have significance.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even if there are unpleasant aspects connected with that, to not deny the significance and just see everything as basically equal, like there is no father, there is no mother, and just say, well, it's... they're just all human beings.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can extend that principle further.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then,
[SPEAKER_01]: In the wrong way, start taking things apart, as if it almost doesn't exist.
[SPEAKER_01]: That would be a sort of continuation of that same wrong view.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the fact is that, as an infant, you're fully dependent on, let's say, parents or caretakers generally, and without their support, you simply wouldn't have made it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there's another discourse where the Buddha, in fact, indicates that it's not easy to repay what one's parents have done.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there are some telling similes there as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, to to see that...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then the question is, yeah, do you have a say in the significance that things have?
[SPEAKER_01]: For example, that's a good question to ask in this context.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, am I creating the significance of things that I encounter in my world, or is that something that I sort of find myself in?
[SPEAKER_02]: What?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, because it's not that people want... it's not that...
[SPEAKER_00]: The problem, basically, is that you would start denying, naturally, when you try to overcome suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: The natural direction is, again, as you said, to start denying the significance of things, because the significance of things is misunderstood to be suffering, or is misunderstood to be greed, aversion, and delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, for example,
[SPEAKER_00]: You would confuse the fact that there is a special significance to your parents, as you said, because they have raised you and they have, like, it just doesn't matter what you do, for better or worse.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you hate your parents, it's always going to have some sort of special significance.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, if you then start thinking that, you know, being free from craving, for example,
[SPEAKER_00]: means not to... that, you know, your parents don't matter anymore because you have no attachment, you have no... you have no concern for the world, you've abandoned all concern for the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you would be implicitly assuming, like you would be overshooting the mark,
[SPEAKER_00]: And seeing, oh, so I have to also deny the significance of these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: In order to accomplish freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, that denial extends to very subtle attitudes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you know, people say, well, everything is just constantly changing.
[SPEAKER_00]: None of this really exists.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, when they try to mix dhamma with science, like, it's just atoms and and the subatomic particles.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or in behaving the way I do because of my genes or DNA, which I inherited from my parents, so we can take out the blame, which is sort of an inverted significance almost.
[SPEAKER_03]: Or on top of the, like, oh, there's no mother, it's just a collection of add-ons.
[SPEAKER_03]: And, I guess, go the other way, while simultaneously doing the exact same thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: This might be for the maybe intense meditator who's like, oh, you know, it's not actually a mother, it's just a collection of like visual data.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, even if you don't talk with scientific terms, if you say, oh, no, no, that's just a perception, that's just a sight, and you might be, like, genuinely trying to practice the dhamma, like, because the Buddha says, see, everything is just, you know, in terms of the six sense bases of the five aggregates, but you're going the wrong way.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're using it to basically, essentially, try to say, there is no mother and there's no father, because it's just a feeling, it's just a perception.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's on the wrong level.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to see, yes, it is just a feeling and just a perception that has a very great significance, like, compared to the other things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the point is that you need to be basically, uh, under, uh, acknowledging that things have a certain significance and then, within that basis, you, you know, develop the practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not like, take a shortcut, basically.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you want to understand
[SPEAKER_00]: You let it be what it is, and then you overcome your greed, your aversion, your delusion, in regard to the significance.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's a subtle distinction that people wouldn't see.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's the same with, you know, acknowledging that there are ascetics and brahmins who realize this world and proclaim it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That too is of significance, because if it wasn't like that,
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, what are you even practicing?
[SPEAKER_01]: Right?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, to have that faith, like, yeah, there are people who see these things for themselves, and based on that actual knowledge that they have, they are capable of expounding that.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't have that,
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, where's your practice?
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, either you want to become a Buddha yourself, which is again overshooting the mark, because that's not quite necessary.
[SPEAKER_01]: There already was a Buddha who has taught the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the goal is not to become a Buddha, just become an Arhat.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's good enough, basically.
[SPEAKER_02]: And connected with that, there can also be a view, like, that the truth is sort of like
[SPEAKER_00]: There are different truths, let's put it that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you know, when people try to mix all the different religions and say, you know, they're all talking about the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think this is sometimes called perennial philosophy, which is the overall term which says that basically all spiritual or religious traditions
[SPEAKER_01]: They spring from the same source and they point to the same truth.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, for many people, that's pleasing to hold that view.
[SPEAKER_01]: But why is that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, in the end, it doesn't actually really matter what you do.
[SPEAKER_01]: As long as it's half religious or spiritual, for lack of better words, you can't go wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that becomes a justification for
[SPEAKER_01]: A massive lack of discernment, because we can just do this, that, and the other, and you think that if you just put it all on top of one another, it counts as progress.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you don't have to recognize the fact that, no, there is right and wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, there is.
[SPEAKER_00]: There has to be some distinction between, like, not everything that you do
[SPEAKER_00]: In the name of spirituality, it can't be considered right.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are things that are taking you away from freedom, from greed, aversion and delusion, which is what the Buddha described as spirituality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just anything that you might regard as less mundane than the things that you're used to.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the other part.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need to have a recognition that
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just that there is a possibility to understand things, as it says that there are ascetics and brahmins who proclaim the world after having understood it, but that, eh... as the Buddha said in one of those suttas, he said, like, he came to his ascetics and asked them, oh, is there one culmination or are there many?
[SPEAKER_00]: I think that's Majjhima Nikaya 11.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said, like, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: And he said, if they would answer rightly, they would say, there is one culmination.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, he asked, is that culmination for one who is free from greed, aversion, delusion, or one who is not free from those things?
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, basically, setting forth those criteria that
[SPEAKER_00]: There has to be that distinction, basically, between... Not just anything that you would regard as liberation counts.
[SPEAKER_00]: It has to be, in terms of greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: That would often not be emphasized.
[SPEAKER_00]: Um, in terms of, like, when people talk about religious experiences and stuff, even in the context of Buddhism, um, you know, you might hear them talking about all sorts of other things, except, you know, how much, uh, concern for the world and, and, and, uh, desire and aversion has been destroyed.
[SPEAKER_00]: More like, I had this, these magical insights and stuff that, that I didn't have before, but, you know, what, that, that part that is,
[SPEAKER_00]: That is kind of the goalpost, or the thing that you should be aiming for, is not really being addressed.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, that's another form of view that could obstruct the practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, what is the freedom about, in the first place?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the goal about?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so people might actually, genuinely, on account of having some teaching or other, have an initial sense of relief, but that... but there needs to be a further discernment than that, because, you know, indulging in sensual pleasure can also give relief, but that is going in the wrong direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you cannot just say, oh, I feel more at ease, or I feel a sense that the pressure has been... therefore it's moving in the right direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or delighting in being, as the Buddha said, like there's a...
[SPEAKER_00]: There's different things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, there's ascetics who, like, even back in the day, they wouldn't be crudely engaging in sensuality, but they would be getting gratification out of their views and out of their practices.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, as we discussed before, in the discussion about virtue and assurances.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: All of that comes within mundane right view, like having a direction of where you're actually going.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just anything that you start with, believing that that's what the dhamma is about.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can take it for granted and start practicing with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, essentially, that would be more of a
[SPEAKER_00]: You would gain... like, 99% of the work is to question the assumptions that you're starting with.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not to just go with those assumptions and then try to build something on top of it, essentially.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what... but that's more pleasant because, like... Because one finds a full sense of safety and security on the level of use, precisely.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the right thing to do, so to say, in the practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's that questioning of what... what are the views that I'm starting with?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do I... am I, you know, on some subtle level, not acknowledging the fact that there is mother and father, that there is action, that there are results of those actions?
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I denying that, for example, even the the one we're talking about now, like,
[SPEAKER_00]: That there are ascetics and brahmins who have realized this world and the next.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I've even heard some people saying that, you know, freedom from greed, aversion and delusion is not actually possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: That, you know, because we are primates, we're human primates, we have these animal sort of drives, and so there are things that we can't help to... like, we can't help, for example, to have sexual desire, because we are biologically wired to have those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or that... so then they would confuse that with
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, freedom is not possible, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, they would still be trying to practice the dhamma, but now with all sorts of other views that have nothing to do with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those are basically... all of those are essentially ways of not taking responsibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the fundamental... That's the common thread that runs through that whole description.
[SPEAKER_01]: In fact, there's another sutra where the Buddha was questioning groups of ascetics and then, you know, he was saying like, if someone holds the view that all pleasure and pain that is experienced right now is the result of what was done in the past,
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, would that be right view or wrong view?
[SPEAKER_01]: And then the Buddha questioned those aesthetics and they held that view.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, yeah, if that's someone's view, that will again inhibit personal responsibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then it goes on to say, like, if someone thinks that whatever pleasure and pain they experience is the result of a creator God, for example,
[SPEAKER_01]: That's also, in the end, going to be problematic.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, you see, if someone accepts that view, then, in the end, you would regard him, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: God, as responsible for what's happening, and not yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you cannot, at the same time, hold the view that you are responsible for abandoning unwholesome and developing wholesome, and at the same time say that all of this is the result of some being that
[SPEAKER_01]: That is basically putting the strings behind the scene.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a contradiction.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not sustainable.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can also... it doesn't even need to be God.
[SPEAKER_00]: You could have a belief, the thing I just said, that, oh, it's this biological hormones and stuff that creates my actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, or brain chemistry.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not me choosing to do these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's basically like the the biology by itself is making these motions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's just a...
[SPEAKER_00]: Essentially the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't talk about God, but it is a belief that another, like something else, is doing the actions for you, and that will prevent you from actually developing yourself, because...
[SPEAKER_00]: All of it, as the Buddha said, suffering is born from kammā.
[SPEAKER_00]: Suffering is born from action.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, if you don't accept that there is action in the first place, then you're basically covering up the the problem, so as to kind of, say, you have a bunch of dirt in a room, and instead of cleaning it up, you just put a big big tarp over it, and then... And then try to look out about it, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but it is... you see, to some extent that might still be pleasing to people, because it takes the... it takes to some extent the burden or the weight off their own shoulders.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the whole point is, as we discussed in an earlier talk, that one will be incapable of freeing oneself from suffering if one does not fully take responsibility, not just for this or that action, but for the fact that one finds oneself in the world at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: That has got to be the starting point, and then you start to work from within that situation, see if you can find a way out.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's again the thing of authenticity that we were talking about.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's, eh... that, eh... recognition that if you're not free, if you want to put it that way, it's... it's your fault.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, nothing else, nothing in the world can be blamed for you not being free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even, like, you know,
[SPEAKER_00]: If it's
[SPEAKER_00]: The most trying circumstances, like, you were born in, or you found the dhamma too late, and you already had, you know, too many defilements, or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no such thing as that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you always have a choice to give up greed, aversion, and delusion right now.
[SPEAKER_00]: You might not want to do it, but there's always something that you can be doing to be closer, and that's all you should be concerned with.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like,
[SPEAKER_00]: There is anything that I can do in that direction, basically, if I just lament that, you know,
[SPEAKER_00]: Something else is imposing these defilements on me, and I can't overcome them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, there's nothing you can do.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's my karma.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's too bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's another thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a big one.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, especially, you know, people... Because you can see, like, this...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this is the mundane right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, it's talking about there is action.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is good and bad action.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, some buddhists, generally, like, trying to have that view very much.
[SPEAKER_00]: They would believe so much in kamma that they would say, well, look, I have been trying to practice for so many years now, and the reason why I'm not able to achieve enlightenment is because I have all this bad kamma from the past.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, like, I need to stop practicing, focus on making merit, so that in the future life, I will be able to actually reach nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then,
[SPEAKER_00]: Funny thing is, like, people don't realize, but the the Jains were saying exactly the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: When they were saying, the Buddha would ask them, like, so why are you doing all these, you know, self-mortification stuff, and then they would say, well, because we have so much bad kamma, by doing this stuff,
[SPEAKER_00]: We wear away the results of our bad actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, the Buddha asked them, so, do you see?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you have, like, recollection of your past lives to know that you actually did all that bad kamma?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, they say, no, we don't.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, and then, in the end, what the answer was, like,
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the view is simply pleasing and agreeable to us.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, with this asceticism, we find... And then he also asks, like, do you see I've worn away this much bad kamma, and there's still that much to be worn away.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then we're basically completely puzzled.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, this is like the vipassana movement.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's been this accumulation of things that you need to erode away through your concentration, perhaps.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, in general, like, if you believe that the defilements...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, the thing we often talk about, like, when you need to get rid of your thoughts, or you believe you need to get rid of your thoughts in order to be at peace, you essentially think that these things that come by themselves,
[SPEAKER_00]: are responsible for your suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, the suffering is happening because of this thing is knocking at my door and I can't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if it comes
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, it's that thing's fault.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can see that's how deep the view that this not taking mundane right view goes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, just not taking responsibility for your own greed, aversion, delusion, even through supposedly practicing the dhamma, like through meditation and stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's eh... that's why I started by saying it's a much more deeply rooted thing that people... that people realize.
[SPEAKER_00]: So... and eh... like the... the... if you... like you don't need to be worried essentially about anything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, what is my view?
[SPEAKER_00]: The view that I approach this whole practice with.
[SPEAKER_00]: That... that should be your concern, not like...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll just... oh, it's because I don't know this method, or that method, or I haven't found out, you know, I haven't studied enough suttas, or... No, it's what are the assumptions, what are the attitudes with which you approach this whole thing, and then keep continuing to review that, but then that's... that's... that's like, you know, when you have a movie,
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't want to be actually knowing that you're watching a movie.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to get absorbed in it, in the movie, so you can enjoy the plot.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you know, if you keep that kind of background perspective, that of questioning your motivations and attitudes while you're doing the practice, the whole thing becomes much more unpleasant than many of the
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if it releases and, you know, mundane pleasure that people might get from the practice, you can't get it anymore, because all that stuff requires you not to be questioning yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: It requires you to kind of get into this hypnosis, basically, where you question what you're doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just
[SPEAKER_00]: Going in this direction, and wherever it takes you, you're blissing out, and that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So... And the waiting goes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, anticipating, praying, praying upon something, so it's...
[SPEAKER_02]: So that attitude of undoing, it's much more, kind of, demanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: It takes... yeah, it takes like a... it's like a dissonance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it's not that it's going to be, you know, agonizing pain the whole time that you start practicing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's more like a... like you have this little sort of noise there that's not... that's not really what you wanted, because it's going against the grain.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_00]: The practice goes against the grain.
[SPEAKER_00]: So...
[SPEAKER_02]: It's also like, you know, undermining the ground on which you are standing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So the whole world is basically to be put in question.
[SPEAKER_02]: The world which you inhabit and feel secure in, pleased with, and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: You might think it's just about, you know, running on top of that ground.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mm-hmm.
[SPEAKER_00]: To where you think you should be going.
[SPEAKER_00]: But no, it's about the fact that, you know, undoing the ground that you're standing on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not a... that's not a...
[SPEAKER_00]: That would be recognized as pleasant when you have trained your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Before that, it's going to be not really... like, you would have to use your discernment to keep going, like, to motivate you to keep going, because the mind in itself doesn't really want to go in that direction.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: I was thinking kind of about, like,
[SPEAKER_03]: You can almost approach it with the view that it's like this epic battle that you kind of suit up for, and you go and you fight it, and it's like this heroic, you know, courageous moment.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, like, it's less... it's not so epic.
[SPEAKER_03]: I guess a good way of putting it is like a good hero's journey story.
[SPEAKER_03]: The hero does not want to be doing the hero's journey.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's one good thing to mention because...
[SPEAKER_00]: When the Buddha talks about the five aggregates, he doesn't say... or the defilements in general, he doesn't say that it's... it's like... like you said, like you're in a battlefield and you see the soldiers coming towards you, like you're gonna fight them head-on.
[SPEAKER_00]: He gave a simile that it's like a rich householder who would have a servant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, the servant would come to him, very nicely, very politely, and start working for him.
[SPEAKER_00]: But from the very start, that servant's goal was to kill the householder.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, while he was sleeping, or when he just wasn't aware,
[SPEAKER_00]: That servant was living in his house the entire time, and then he kills him.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, and the householder came to trust the servant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, and then after a long time, he was caught off guard.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the... all the things that you have to overcome are coming from that sort of indirect direction that you actually have trust in.
[SPEAKER_00]: The things that you think are for your welfare, they're basically the things that are right there waiting to kill you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, any sort of pleasure that you might be getting from the practice,
[SPEAKER_00]: If it hasn't given you the right view, you should be skeptical, because it is very likely that it is the pleasure of the trust in that very thing that, for now, is nice.
[SPEAKER_00]: For now, it's comfortable, but eventually, it's gonna stab you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's this Aṭṭhasūtra about the five aggregates, where the Buddha says that one is devoured by those five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Actually, that's how it gets translated, but I think it actually means, like, I'm itching with...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm itching with these... with form, itching with feeling, itching with...
[SPEAKER_00]: The thing is, in English, that's not really... doesn't really make sense, but that's kind of what it means.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not a... it's coming, like, on that level, like, this thing is itching.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like...
[SPEAKER_00]: On you, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not some sort of, you know, enemy out there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's right there in your personal sort of space.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where the whole problem is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not in anything else that you may blame for, you know, getting rid of your... managing your environment, essentially.
[SPEAKER_03]: Sartra has a play called No Exit.
[SPEAKER_03]: Basically, the premise is these characters are in hell, and hell is like this very kind of mundane.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're just stuck in a room with three people, and they annoy the hell out of you, essentially.
[SPEAKER_03]: And kind of it ends with this culmination.
[SPEAKER_03]: This dude knocking on the door is like, let me out, you know, give me the, like, chains and the fire and the, you know...
[SPEAKER_03]: The torture chair is like anything but this like subtle nagging, you know.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not bad enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the sort of discomfort or the dissonance of existence.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you recognize that responsibility, it's like... it's something like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not a...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like you're carrying a mountain.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think that's what we were discussing the other day.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like the pain of carrying a lot of stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's more like you have a bunch of pointy little rocks in your foot, in your shoe.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's something like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's...
[SPEAKER_00]: The practice, basically, is not... should not be expected to be comfortable, unless you are already far, far, like, beyond.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's another view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, am I expecting the practice to result in pleasure as soon as possible?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or do I recognize that there is a problem here that needs to be fixed?
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, it's not necessarily going to be going to be, you know, a nice ride right away.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, eventually, you want to be free from suffering, but you have to recognize, like anything, in the beginning, it's always a grind, so to say.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I think that's very important.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like what you said also, Lapandu, recognizing one's own attitude.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, link to what you just said, because if one doesn't recognize that, okay, I'm actually wanting to get rid of that, so I'm acting out of aversion and craving, like, my whole practice is based on that, so everything that I can recognize as peaceful or as pleasant is actually
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, and doesn't matter how peaceful it is, it is within the same container.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, that's why, if it is... if it just comes easily to you, kind of at the same time or parallel to your lay life and your possessions and your worldly engagements, and you kind of have it side by side like that, that's a good indication that this other thing is just coming basically within the same... taking place within those same attitudes.
[SPEAKER_00]: that you are used to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it didn't require you to transform your your mind, your way of existing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, just imagine if you had a dog that was
[SPEAKER_00]: That was wild and, you know, or a child that was that was spoiled and, you know, behaving... having bad behavior and suddenly, the next day, it's like an angel.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you might be suspicious that there are some, you know, underlying... it's not a... it didn't magically change like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: The same thing with the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you have been, you know, acting out of greed, aversion, and delusion, and suddenly you find this pleasure, and it's really wonderful, and, you know, all the all the suffering is gone, well, you should be skeptical about that, because...
[SPEAKER_03]: So, one should actually tell yourself, like, it's quite hard, but, like, I don't know what happiness is.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, I don't know, like, I'm suffering and I don't know how to get out.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's quite hard.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Buddha said the whole world sees the pleasant sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches and thoughts, like phenomena, as pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the cessation, the actual thing that's pleasant,
[SPEAKER_00]: ...is seen as unpleasant by the world, which is the cessation of those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he says, the noble ones are the ones who understand that as the true pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have to understand, like, whatever I regard as pleasure, not like I have to get rid of it, because then we get into the same thing we were discussing before, like you want to deny the significance of everything, but you can't take it as the way to enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't assume that if it's pleasant,
[SPEAKER_00]: pleasure is going to rise on its own, but it can't be taken as a vehicle.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's when... because you end up with all sorts of misconceptions, like, you know,
[SPEAKER_00]: Metta, for example, metta practice, like, you assume that you just generate this pleasant feeling, these pleasant feelings, and that's it, like, you're you're already practicing, you know, the... You're on the way to nibbāna, radiating these pleasant feelings all over the place, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you never had to go through any sort of training, like, you just... everything just fit together magically like that, so that's just too good to be true, basically.